<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Colin VanderMeer&#39;s Blog</title>
  <subtitle>This is a longer description about your blog.</subtitle>
  <link href="https://colinvandermeer.github.io/public/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://colinvandermeer.github.io/" />
  <updated>2026-02-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://colinvandermeer.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Colin VanderMeer</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>UNBEATABLE Review</title>
    <link href="https://colinvandermeer.github.io/blog/UnbeatableReview/" />
    <updated>2026-02-09T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://colinvandermeer.github.io/blog/UnbeatableReview/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;style&gt;
  .treble-container {
    display: flex;
    justify-content: center;
    align-items: center;
    margin-top: var(--spacing-md);
    margin-bottom: var(--spacing-md);
  }

  .treble-box {
    display: flex;
    align-items: center;
    padding: var(--spacing-md);
    background: var(--color-secondary);
    border-width: 5px;
    border-color: var(--color-primary);
    border-style: solid;
    border-radius: var(--radius-lg);
    position: relative;
    width: 90%;
  }

  .treble-character {
    flex-shrink: 0;
    cursor: pointer;
    user-select: none;
  }

  .treble-character img {
    height: 30vw;
    object-fit: contain;
  }

  .treble-bubble {
    flex: 1;
    text-align: center;
    min-height: 150px;
    display: flex;
    align-items: center;
    justify-content: center;
    position: relative;
  }

  .treble-bubble &gt; div {
    position: relative;
    width: 100%;
    display: flex;
    align-items: center;
    justify-content: center;
  }

  .treble-bubble img {
    width: 100%;
    height: auto;
    object-fit: contain;
  }

  #bubbleText {
    position: absolute;
    width: 70%;
    font-size: 1.3rem;
    line-height: 1.4;
    margin: 0;
    padding: 0 1rem;
    color: black;
    font-weight: bold;
    left: 22%;
  }

  .mute-button {
    position: absolute;
    bottom: 1rem;
    right: 1rem;
    background: none;
    border: none;
    font-size: 2rem;
    cursor: pointer;
    padding: 0.5rem;
    transition: transform 0.2s;
  }

  .mute-button:hover {
    transform: scale(1.1);
  }

  .mute-button.muted {
    opacity: 0.5;
  }
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think something Treble says during Episode 4 really applies to the game as a whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;treble-container&quot;&gt;
  &lt;div class=&quot;treble-box&quot;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&quot;treble-character&quot; id=&quot;trebleCharacter&quot;&gt;
      &lt;img src=&quot;https://colinvandermeer.github.io/blog/unbeatable/trebleIdle.gif&quot; alt=&quot;treble&quot;&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;treble-bubble&quot; id=&quot;trebleBubble&quot;&gt;
&lt;div&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://colinvandermeer.github.io/blog/unbeatable/bubbleLeft.png&quot; alt=&quot;Speech bubble&quot;&gt;
&lt;p id=&quot;bubbleText&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;button class=&quot;mute-button&quot; id=&quot;muteButton&quot; aria-label=&quot;Toggle mute&quot;&gt;🔊&lt;/button&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script&gt;
  const trebleSounds = [
    &#39;/blog/unbeatable/treble1.mp3&#39;,
    &#39;/blog/unbeatable/treble2.mp3&#39;,
    &#39;/blog/unbeatable/treble3.mp3&#39;,
    &#39;/blog/unbeatable/treble4.mp3&#39;,
    &#39;/blog/unbeatable/treble5.mp3&#39;,
    &#39;/blog/unbeatable/treble6.mp3&#39;
  ];

  const trebleLines = [
    &#39;to me, and i really mean this honestly. it feels like the soul is missing from the thing.&#39;,
    &#39;i&#92;&#39;m not some weird lo-fi purist, but it really is too clean.&#39;,
    &#39;there&#92;&#39;s like... this energy&#92;&#39;s gone from it.&#39;,
    &#39;y&#92;&#39;know, some messiness is &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt;.&#39;,
    &#39;it&#92;&#39;s like... restoring a painting. you have to be careful because... you can scrape paint off alongside the dirt.&#39;,
    &#39;and i think we do a little bit of our painting &lt;em&gt;with&lt;/em&gt; dirt.&#39;
  ];

  const bubbleImages = {
    left: &#39;/blog/unbeatable/bubbleLeft.png&#39;,
    middle: &#39;/blog/unbeatable/bubbleMiddle.png&#39;
  };

  let currentSoundIndex = 0;
  let isMuted = false;
  let isPlaying = false;
  let bubbleAnimationId = null;
  let currentBubble = &#39;left&#39;;

  const trebleCharacter = document.getElementById(&#39;trebleCharacter&#39;);
  const trebleBubble = document.getElementById(&#39;trebleBubble&#39;);
  const muteButton = document.getElementById(&#39;muteButton&#39;);
  const bubbleImg = trebleBubble.querySelector(&#39;img&#39;);
  const bubbleText = document.getElementById(&#39;bubbleText&#39;);

  function startBubbleAnimation() {
    if (bubbleAnimationId) return;
    
    currentBubble = &#39;left&#39;;
    bubbleImg.src = bubbleImages.left;
    
    bubbleAnimationId = setInterval(() =&gt; {
      currentBubble = currentBubble === &#39;left&#39; ? &#39;middle&#39; : &#39;left&#39;;
      bubbleImg.src = currentBubble === &#39;left&#39; ? bubbleImages.left : bubbleImages.middle;
    }, 250);
  }

  function stopBubbleAnimation() {
    if (bubbleAnimationId) {
      clearInterval(bubbleAnimationId);
      bubbleAnimationId = null;
    }
  }

  function playSound() {
    if (isPlaying) return;
    if (currentSoundIndex == 6) {
      currentSoundIndex = 0;
      bubbleText.innerHTML = &quot;&quot;;
      return;
    }

    isPlaying = true;
    bubbleText.innerHTML = trebleLines[currentSoundIndex];
    
    const audio = new Audio(trebleSounds[currentSoundIndex]);
    
    if (!isMuted) {
      audio.onplay = () =&gt; {
        startBubbleAnimation();
      };

      audio.onended = () =&gt; {
        stopBubbleAnimation();
        bubbleImg.src = bubbleImages.left;
        currentSoundIndex = currentSoundIndex + 1;
        isPlaying = false;
      };

      audio.play().catch(err =&gt; console.error(&#39;Error playing sound:&#39;, err));
    } else {
      isPlaying = false;
      currentSoundIndex = currentSoundIndex + 1;
    }
  }

  trebleCharacter.addEventListener(&#39;click&#39;, () =&gt; {
    playSound();
  });

  trebleBubble.addEventListener(&#39;click&#39;, () =&gt; {
    playSound();
  });

  muteButton.addEventListener(&#39;click&#39;, () =&gt; {
    isMuted = !isMuted;
    muteButton.textContent = isMuted ? &#39;🔇&#39; : &#39;🔊&#39;;
    muteButton.classList.toggle(&#39;muted&#39;);
  });
&lt;/script&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>100 Days of macOS</title>
    <link href="https://colinvandermeer.github.io/blog/100daysOfMacos/" />
    <updated>2025-07-23T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://colinvandermeer.github.io/blog/100daysOfMacos/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;The first computer I ever used was a 2007 iMac. I used this computer almost exclusively for 11 years straight, only occasionally having an affair with a windows laptop we also had to run games on there that I couldn&#39;t on the Mac. In 2018 my family bought it&#39;s first desktop gaming computer and I said goodbye to my loyal macOS to jump headfirst into Windows 10.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that day I didn&#39;t touch macOS for the next 6 years of my life. I had a Windows desktop, then a Chromebook, then a Windows laptop which then became a &lt;a href=&quot;https://colinvandermeer.github.io/blog/100daysOfLinux/&quot;&gt;Linux laptop&lt;/a&gt;. Though when that Linux laptop was becoming a bit of a pain to work with (see previous article) I heard that the new M4 MacBook Air was $100 USD cheaper and started at 16gb of ram I decided to fully embrace the apple ecosystem and finally go back to macOS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Good&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Phenomenal Hardware and Battery Life&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m sure by now you&#39;ve heard how good everyone thinks Apple Silicon is, and it is that good. The way Apple has finely tuned every single piece of macOS to work flawlessly with the rest of it&#39;s hardware is as good as everyone says it is. I&#39;ve never used a more performant laptop or a laptop with battery life this good, and the MacBook manages to do both at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;App Support&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Compared to Linux, macOS has a great library of software. Most modern software is designed to run on macOS since it&#39;s the second most popular operating system in the world, and if Apple wants software on their platform they have more than enough money to throw at developers to make it happen. During the switch to Apple Silicon, Adobe released a beta version of Photoshop for Apple Silicon day and date with it&#39;s release.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Spotlight Search / Raycast&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I adore Spotlight Search. I always opened apps on Windows by pressing the Windows key and typing the app name. The problem is it would only work half the time, and the other half the time it would open Bing. On macOS this works 100% of the time because of spotlight search. I also use a replacement for the default spotlight search called Raycast which is basically spotlight search on steroids and VC funded. Raycast even states in it&#39;s manifest that it&#39;s &amp;quot;inspired by early command line interfaces, where you could take any action without the distractions&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing I didn&#39;t think I&#39;d like in Raycast is it&#39;s heavy push of AI, but with some recent updates I&#39;ve actually started appreciating it. I really like the &amp;quot;Quick AI&amp;quot; that you can access by opening Raycast, pushing tab, and typing whatever you want. It&#39;s become a really fast tool for quickly getting general information when I&#39;m trying to code or write something. This feature became actually usable for me when they added &amp;quot;Bring Your Own Key&amp;quot; support which allows you to manually hook Raycast AI up to your own OpenAI / Anthropic / Google API key. And since Google&#39;s Gemini API allows you to get Gemini 2.5 Flash for 250 requests free, I never run into any rate limits and I don&#39;t have to pay for it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Bad&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Software Updates&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming from Arch Linux makes macOS update system feel terrible in comparison. Every time I have to wait 10 minutes for my MacBook to install it&#39;s new update I miss my package manager that was able to update my entire desktop environment in the background and hot reload it to the new version without me noticing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Cmd (⌘) key&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;macOS takes what Windows performs perfectly fine on one key and splits it across three different keys. One of the most important ways I navigate text on Windows is by holding the Ctrl key and using the arrows to jump between words, using the shift arrows to select text words at a time, or using the backspace key to delete words at a time. macOS moves this feature to the option (alt) key but keeps all the copying and pasting on the command key. So instead of holding one key when wanting to navigate around and edit text, you have to remember to hold one key and then switch to the other when you want to copy and paste.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This also means that all of the standard hotkeys for thing on Windows and Linux have been completely reworked to deal with this new modifier key. For instance, opening developer tools on a web browser for Windows and Linux is &lt;code&gt;Ctrl + Shift + I&lt;/code&gt; whereas on macOS it&#39;s &lt;code&gt;Cmd + Option + I&lt;/code&gt;. Firefox&#39;s hotkey to open pip video is &lt;code&gt;Ctrl + Shift + ]&lt;/code&gt; but on macOS it&#39;s &lt;code&gt;Cmd + Option + Shift + ]&lt;/code&gt; so it doesn&#39;t even get changed consistently!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Gatekeeper&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Never before have I had to fight with an operating system so much just to make it run the file I want. macOS is downright determined to prevent you from running any app that isn&#39;t properly notarized by Apple. This isn&#39;t just &amp;quot;Open System Settings. Click Privacy &amp;amp; Security, scroll down, and click the Open Anyway button.&amp;quot; I&#39;ve run into software that this won&#39;t even work on. I have to manually clear all attributes and force my own code signature on it, and if you even open the app once it&#39;ll never work even after you do all those things. A &amp;quot;user friendly operating system&amp;quot; shouldn&#39;t require users to use the terminal just to open an app.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;image width=&quot;50%&quot; style=&quot;margin-top: -20px&quot; src=&quot;/images/100Mac/gatekeeper.webp&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;display: block; text-align: center; margin-top: -20px;&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;xattr -cr &amp;lt;APP&amp;gt; &amp;amp;&amp;amp; codesign --force --deep --sign - &amp;lt;APP&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; is your friend&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Closing Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;macOS good &lt;image style=&quot;height: calc(var(--font-size-base) * 2); vertical-align: middle; display: inline;&quot; src=&quot;/images/blobhajParty.gif&quot;&gt;&lt;/image&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/image&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>100 Days of Linux</title>
    <link href="https://colinvandermeer.github.io/blog/100daysOfLinux/" />
    <updated>2025-07-22T00:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://colinvandermeer.github.io/blog/100daysOfLinux/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;During my first year of High School I was gifted a Surface Laptop Go to help with my schoolwork. It was a pretty decent laptop with &lt;span title=&quot;The cooling on this laptop was atrocious. It was constantly full fan and thermal throttling if you tried to do anything. And the battery life barely lasted a day&quot; style=&quot;text-decoration: underline; text-decoration-style: dashed; cursor: help;&quot;&gt;some flaws&lt;/span&gt; but for that time in my life it was perfect. Unfortunately 3 years later it had slowed down to a crawl, it&#39;s initial startup would take upwards of two minutes and general navigation was becoming tedious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is when I had the idea to install Linux to breath some new life into this aging laptop. I had some general experience with Linux before, running Debian 10 through Crostini on ChromeOS to run a few select Linux apps (mostly games) and using Linux in a server setting to power the leaderboard for &lt;a href=&quot;https://colinvandermeer.github.io/projects/#FeedBluebell&quot;&gt;Feed Bluebell&lt;/a&gt;, but I&#39;d never &amp;quot;daily driven&amp;quot; Linux as my main OS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://colinvandermeer.github.io/images/100Linux/Crostini.png&quot; alt=&quot;A screenshot of the Crostini terminal on ChromeOS&quot;&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Crostini terminal on ChromeOS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I chose EndeavourOS + KDE Plasma as my Distro of choice since it&#39;s basically Arch Linux with a graphical installer and sets up a few extra sane default configurations. I chose an Arch base because of its rolling release model seeming nice after dealing with outdated dependency hell on ChromeOS&#39;s outdated Debian and the AUR sounding like a good package distribution model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I installed EndeavourOS on December 6th 2024 and daily drove that same install for 124 days to April 8th 2025 when I bought a M4 Macbook Air switched over to MacOS. In this blog post I&#39;ll talk about the good and the bad with my experience switching from Windows to daily driving Linux.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Good&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Pacman / AUR&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of my favourite parts of Linux is it&#39;s package management philosophy. Having a centralized repository for 90% of the software for your system just makes sense and is way better than the searching for exe files on random websites for Windows. And since you have all of your software downloaded and tracked from one place you can update your entire system just by running &lt;code&gt;pacman -Syu&lt;/code&gt; (or &lt;code&gt;yay&lt;/code&gt; as I did) and everything just updates and live reloads in the background. It&#39;s just such an elegant solution that all operating systems should strive for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://colinvandermeer.github.io/images/100Linux/ILuvPacman.png&quot; alt=&quot;A screenshot of Pacman showing all the packages it&#39;s updating&quot;&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;image-caption&quot;&gt;Upgrade your entire system, in the background, while you work, and it&#39;ll only take up an extra 3mb of disk space. Thanks Pacman &amp;lt;3&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Performance&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the main reasons I finally switched to Linux was to solve some of the terrible performance issues my laptop had on Windows, and I feel confident in saying those were mostly resolved. Overall the system performed much better with the lighter operating system on it, with a specific standout being the boot time which went from &amp;gt;2min to around 15 seconds. A few things did take a performance hit (notably Intel QSV hardware video decoding only worked with Chromium under X11?) But overall performance was much improved by the Linux switch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Morals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Linux is Free Open Source Software built by people to serve people, not to serve shareholders. In a world where every software update only seems to make every program worse in order to extract more money from you, it&#39;s nice to run an operating system completely removed from that system. Knowing my system was my system designed by people with my best interests at heart &lt;!-- Other than Jia Tan obviously --&gt; is just a nice to have feeling you can&#39;t get anywhere else &lt;br&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;small-text&quot;&gt; Well you can get the exact negative of that feeling when trying to save your documents from the all consuming wrath of OneDrive when setting up Windows &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The Bad&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Battery Life&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After installing Linux my battery life went from &amp;quot;&lt;em&gt;Might last the whole day if you&#39;re lucky&lt;/em&gt;&amp;quot; to &amp;quot;&lt;em&gt;This will die in the middle of the day 100% of the time&lt;/em&gt;&amp;quot;. This was annoying, but wasn&#39;t really a deal breaker because I had already become accustom to charging my laptop halfway through the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Touchpad&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was one of three huge unsolvable issues that tainted my Linux experience the whole time I was using it. The touchpad just felt bad to use, and the especially big problem was the scrolling. First, the scrolling was way too fast, no matter what setting I set it to in setting. Second, and the main problem, on every other touchpad device if you scroll down with speed and release the scroll will keep traveling with inertia, and if you tap it will stop. Try this on any Windows Laptop, MacBook, iPhone, or Android device you have and it&#39;ll do this same thing. Not Linux. For some reason Linux doesn&#39;t stop the inertia scroll if you put your fingers back on the touchpad. This made navigating any website a pain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The 400mhz curse&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some unknown reason if I booted my computer from shutdown when it had less than 10% battery the CPU would be locked to running between 400-700mhz until I rebooted the computer when it was &amp;gt;10% battery. For context this chip has a base clock of 1Ghz and a boost clock of 3.6Ghz, and when running not in this locked mode it would average jumping between 1.5-2.5Ghz. This meant if the computer ever died (which it did often) it would become completely unbearable to use until I waited ~5 minutes for it to charge above 10% battery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;WiFi Issues&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After 3 months into daily driving Linux a weird issue started happening. Randomly about once a day for 5 minutes the WiFi on my laptop would just stop working, it didn&#39;t disconnect or show any signs on why it would stop working, it just did. This was unacceptable for the laptop that I was doing all my school work on and was the main thing that pushed me into upgrading to a new MacBook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Closing Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall I really enjoyed my time using Linux and while I&#39;ve upgraded to running MacOS, there are still many things I miss from running linux. I still keep that Linux laptop around too, it&#39;s useful whenever I need to read a USB drive or connect to a printer (Linux is &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; good at reading USB drives and connecting to printers)&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>